Guide to the Phyllis Chesler Papers, 1968-2003 RL.00221
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- International Committee for Women of the Wall Series, 1988-2001, 40 boxes
  - Kotel Archive Subseries
    Compiled prior to accession, the archive is divided into the following categories: Legal, Media, Publicity, Temporary, Internal Correspondence, External Correspondence, Writing, and Development/Fundraising. A printed inventory came with the collection and is in the first box. Materials are grouped according to categories outlined in the inventory, but do not follow the numerical order specified within categories.
    - Legal (Box WOW28)
    - Media (Box WOW28-30)
    - Publicity (Box WOW30-31, 41)
    - Temporary (Box WOW31-32)
    - Internal Correspondence (Box WOW32-33)
    - External Correspondence (Box WOW33-34)
    - Writing (Box WOW35)
    - Development/Fundraising (Box WOW35-36)
  - Administrative Files Subseries
    Includes board meeting agendas and notes, newsletters, press releases, contact lists, and files related to the budget and fundraising.
    - Administrative Files (Box WOW37)
  - Media Files Subseries
    Includes clippings of print media coverage related to Women of the Wall, some authored by members of the ICWOW.
    - Media Files (Box WOW39-40)
  - Audiocassettes Subseries
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
    Cassettes are listed below as labeled. An audiocassette interview with Anat Hoffman remains with materials for Women of the Wall: Claiming Sacred Ground. Audiocassettes can also be found in the Kotel Archives Subseries.
    - Dworkin-Chesler in Tel Aviv and Barb Becker, 1988 (Box WOW38)
    - Assorted, 1988-1989 (Box WOW38)
    - Nabila, 1988 November 27 (Box WOW38)
    - Gigi Finkel, 1988 December (Box WOW38)
    - Dworkin, 1988 December 1 (Box WOW38)
    - At the Kotel Excerpts, 1988 December 1 (Box WOW38)
    - Post-Conference, 1988 December 2 (Box WOW38)
    - PC on Kotel, 1988 December 8 (Box WOW38)
    - PC Workshop, 1988 December 18 (Box WOW38)
    - In Jerusalem, 1989? (Box WOW38)
    - Women's Prayer at Kotel, 1989 November 24 (Box WOW38)
    - Hebrew University, 1989 November 29 (Box WOW38)
    - Kotel Davening - Dub, 1989 November 30 (Box WOW38)
    - At the Kotel - Dub, 1989 November 30 (Box WOW38)
    - Panel, Hebrew University, 1989 November 30 (Box WOW38)
    - El Al on Kotel, 1989 December 3-4 (Box WOW38)
    - Kotel, 1989 December 6 (Box WOW38)
    - PC and MH on ICWK, 1991 February 8 (Box WOW38)
    - Jessie Bonn/ICWK, 1994 November 3 (Box WOW38)
    - Shul Benefit/WOW Events, 2000 February 13 (Box WOW38)
    - ICWOW Meeting, 2000 June 4, 3 tapes (Box WOW38)
    - Eliav, March 14, 2 tapes (Box WOW38)
    - Unlabeled, 2000 (Box WOW38)
- On The Issues Series 1987-1998, 12 boxes
  The On The Issues Series contains correspondence, article and column drafts, pre-published and published issue files, financial materials, meeting notes, and other papers related to the publication of On The Issues, a quarterly feminist magazine. Chesler served as an editor-at-large for the magazine, and she correspondedfrequently and worked closely with its publisher and editor-in-chief, Merle Hoffman.
  - Published issues, Volume VII, 1987 (Box OTI1)
  - Work in Progress, 1988 (Box OTI1)
  - Activities, March 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Activities, April 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Activities, May 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Activities/Expenses sheets, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Bills paid, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Bills to be processed, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Choices correspondence, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Expenses, January-February 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Expenses, February-March 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - General correspondence, January-June 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Incoming, April 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Lowry, Beverly, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Pieces, March 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Review requests sent, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Talking Feminist, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Various mailing lists, 1989 (Box OTI1)
  - Production schedule, 1989-1990 (Box OTI1)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1989-1990 (Box OTI1)
  - Kotel, summer 1990 (Box OTI1)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1990 (Box OTI1)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1991 (Box OTI1)
  - Column Draft, May 1992 (Box OTI1)
  - Correspondence and drafts, 1992 (Box OTI1)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1992 (Box OTI1)
  - Phyllis Chesler interview requests, 1992 (Box OTI1)
  - Correspondence and drafts, 1993 (Box OTI1)
  - Fax File, 1993 (Box OTI1)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1993 (Box OTI2)
  - Subscriber survey and publicity, 1993 (Box OTI2)
  - Tribeca/Brownfield, January 1993 (Box OTI2)
  - Wuornos update drafts, 1993 (Box OTI2)
  - OTI published issues [incomplete], 1993 (Box OTI2)
  - Clippings and notes, 1994 (Box OTI2)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1994 (Box OTI2)
  - Correspondence, May-July 1994 (Box OTI2)
  - Correspondence, July-November 1994 (Box OTI2)
  - Correspondence, December 1994 (Box OTI2)
  - Deluca, September 1994 (Box OTI2)
  - Deluca Column: assorted photos from Eleanor Pam, 1994 (Box OTI3)
  - Deluca Column: Research material, correspondence, and drafts, 1994, 2 folders (Box OTI3)
  - Deluca final, 1994 (Box OTI3)
  - Deluca/Stamen, 1994 (Box OTI3)
  - Dershowitz, circa 1994 (Box OTI3)
  - Henson OTI event, 1994 (Box OTI3)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1994, 2 folders (Box OTI3)
  - Merle Hoffman OTI bill, 1994 (Box OTI3)
  - New column, December 1994 (Box OTI3)
  - Rimland drafts, Winter 1994, 2 folders (Box OTI4)
  - When They Call You Crazy, summer 1994 (Box OTI4)
  - Chesler's February OTI column, 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - Feminist Foremothers, 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - Feminist Foremothers long version, 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - Feminist Foremothers short, 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - Merle Hoffman, 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI, January 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI, February 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI, March 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI, April 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI, June 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI, July 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI, August 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - OTI Pack 6-6, 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: correspondence and drafts, 1995 (Box OTI4)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: early discarded drafts, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: final with timeline, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: final and translation, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: media list, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: page proofs, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: press release, letter responses, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Rape in Bosnia article: timeline, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Recent OTI columns, 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Time sheets/story ideas, summer 1995 (Box OTI5)
  - Annual retreat, 1996 (Box OTI5)
  - Child support column previous drafts, 1996, 2 folders (Box OTI5)
  - Choices financials, 1996 (Box OTI5)
  - Column ideas, 1996 (Box OTI5)
  - Correspondence and other papers, January-February 1996, 3 folders (Box OTI5-OTI6)
  - Correspondence, March 1996 (Box OTI6)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1996 (Box OTI6)
  - Correspondence and other papers, June 1996, 2 folders (Box OTI6)
  - Correspondence, July 1996 (Box OTI6)
  - Correspondence, September 1996 (Box OTI6)
  - Correspondence, October 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - Correspondence and drafts, November-December 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - Feminist Prayers, 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - Legacy columns 6.18A/B, 6.19A, 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - Next Issue [Winter 1997], 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - PC book review, 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - PC stories, 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - PC story contents possibilities, 1996 (Box OTI7)
  - Phyllis Chesler's In-Hand Story Idea Submissions, 1996 (Box OTI8)
  - Pre-published issue files, April 1996 (Box OTI8)
  - Pre-published issue files, October 1996 (Box OTI8)
  - S.L. Bender piece, 1996 (Box OTI8)
  - Stories to review, 1996 (Box OTI8)
  - Tickler file, 1996 (Box OTI8)
  - Trish Wilson, 1996 (Box OTI8)
  - Articles- Griffen, Gage, etc., 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - Aryana Friedman, 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - Bulletin board, front hallway, 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - Chronic Fatigue Syndrome article, 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - CFS article correspondence, 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - CFS article/email, 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - CFS article- Phyllis's copy, 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - CFIDS final, 1997 (Box OTI8)
  - Column, February-March 1997 (Box OTI9)
  - Correspondence and other papers, January-March 1997, 2 folders (Box OTI9)
  - Correspondence, April 1997 (Box OTI9)
  - Correspondence, May 1997 (Box OTI9)
  - Correspondence, June 1997, 2 folders (Box OTI9)
  - Correspondence, July 1997 (Box OTI9)
  - Correspondence, August 1997 (Box OTI9)
  - For Merle to look at, 1997 (Box OTI9)
  - Ideas, 1997 (Box OTI9)
  - Kotel article, 1997, 4 folders (Box OTI9-OTI10)
  - Kotel final, 1997 (Box OTI10)
  - Letters to a Young Feminist column, 1997 (Box OTI10)
  - Notes/memos to OTI, 1997 (Box OTI10)
  - Pre-published issue files, February 1997 (Box OTI10)
  - Pre-published issue files, March 1997 (Box OTI10)
  - Pre-published issue files, summer 1997 (Box OTI10)
  - Pre-published issue files, October 1997 (Box OTI11)
  - Pre-published issue files, November 1997 (Box OTI11)
  - Published issues [incomplete], 1997 (Box OTI11)
  - Staff, 1997 (Box OTI11)
  - Story ideas, April 1997 (Box OTI11)
  - Summary of deadlines, 1997 (Box OTI11)
  - To do, 1997 (Box OTI11)
  - Story ideas, 1997-1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Chesler OTI stories, August 1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Column/letter to Jan, 1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Correspondence, January 1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Correspondence, February 1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Correspondence, March 1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Correspondence, April 1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Correspondence, June 1998 (Box OTI11)
  - Correspondence, July 1998, 2 folders (Box OTI11-12)
  - Laurie Rosen, 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - A Meditation on the Sea, 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Mother column, May 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Mothers, 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Nature Elegy, 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Planning, spring 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Pre-published issue files, March 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Pre-published issue files, summer 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Pre-published issue files, winter 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Shulamith Firestone, 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Solstice, 1998 (Box OTI12)
  - Story meeting, July 1998 (Box OTI12)
- Chronic Fatigue Syndrome Series 1991-1997, 1 box
  The Chronic Fatigue Syndrome Series contains Chesler's research and drafts of writings on Chronic Fatigue Syndrome, also referred to by the acronyms CFS and CFIDS. There is also material related to Chronic Fatigue Syndrome in the On the Issues Series. See box OTI8.
  - American Health, 1996-1997 (Box CFS1)
  - Aviva Rahmani: Paintings before CFS, Schedules after CFS, 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - CFIDS manuscript, 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - CFS article, 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - CFS points to input, 1996 (Box CFS1)
  - CFS research, 1996 (Box CFS1)
  - CPAR, August 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - CPAR, September 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - CPAR address book, 1996 (Box CFS1)
  - Critiques of studies, 1996 (Box CFS1)
  - Gulf War illness, 1996-1997 (Box CFS1)
  - It's All In Your Head, 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - Mary Schweitzer article, 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - Maryann Spurgin article, 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - New York Times CFS letter, October 1996 (Box CFS1)
  - Notes, inputted (Box CFS1)
  - Osler's Web, 1996 (Box CFS1)
  - OTI/CFIDS in progress, 1997 (Box CFS1)
  - Outgoing CPAR mail, 1996 (Box CFS1)
  - Phyllis Chesler's chronic fatigue letter to friends, 1991 (Box CFS1)
  - "Scientific" studies, 1996-1997 (Box CFS1)
- Accession 2003-0246
  - Audiovisual materials
    - Nikki Craft, WBAI, December 1991; 1:00:30
      Scope and Contents
      Interview with activist Nikki Craft on WBAI radio, New York.
      - Original audiocassette (Box Acc. 03/246:Box 109, Audio-cassette RL00221-CS-0001)
      - Digital audio preservation file (Digital-materials RL00221-SET-0001, Audio-file RL00221-CS-0001_001.wav, Audio-file RL00221-CS-0001_002.wav)